<text xml:id="Poe_062112">
    <front>
        <titlePage>
            <titlePart type="main">THE INCOMPLETE WORKS OF EDGAR ALLAN POE:</titlePart>
            <titlePart type="sub">A VERY BRIEF ANTHOLOGY</titlePart>

            <docImprint>
                <publisher>Association of College and Research Libraries</publisher>
                <docDate>2012</docDate>
            </docImprint>
        </titlePage>
        <pb/>
        <div type="contents">
            <head>TABLE OF CONTENTS.</head>

            <list>
                <item>The Raven ............................................... 1</item>
                <item>The Angel of the Odd ......................................... 2</item>
                <item>Scenes from “Politian”....................................... 7</item>
                <item>Notes ............................................... 10</item>
            </list>
        </div>
    </front>
    <pb n="1"/>
    <body>
        <div type="poem">
            <head>THE RAVEN.</head>

            <lg type="stanza">
                <l>Once upon a midnight dreary, while I pondered, weak and weary,</l>
                <l>Over many a quaint and curious volume of forgotten lore,</l>
                <l>While I nodded, nearly napping, suddenly there came a tapping,</l>
                <l>As of some one gently rapping, rapping at my chamber door.</l>
                <l>“'Tis some visiter,” I muttered, “tapping at my chamber door— </l>
                <l>Only this, and nothing more.”</l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="stanza">
                <l>Ah, distinctly I remember it was in the bleak Decebmer,</l>
                <l>And each separate dying ember wrought its ghost upon the floor.</l>
                <l>Eagerly I wished the morrow;—vainly I had sought to borrow</l>
                <l>From my books surcease of sorrow—sorrow for the lost Lenore1—</l>
                <l>For the rare and radiant maiden whom the angels name Lenore—</l>
                <l>Nameless here for evermore.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="stanza">
                <l>And the silken sad uncertain rustling of each purple curtain</l>
                <l>Thrilled me—filled me with fantastic terrors never felt before;</l>
                <l>So that now, to still the beating of my heart, I stood repeating</l>
                <l>“'Tis some visiter entreating entrance at my chamber door—</l>
                <l>Some late visiter entreating entrance at my chamber door;—</l>
                <l>This it is, and nothing more.”</l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="stanza">
                <l>Presently my soul grew stronger; hesitating then no longer,</l>
                <l>“Sir,” said I, “or Madam, truly your forgiveness I implore;</l>
                <l>But the fact is I was napping, and so gently you came rapping,</l>
                <l>And so faintly you came tapping, tapping at my chamber door,</l>
                <l>That I scarce was sure I heard you”—here I opened wide the door;—</l>
                <l>Darkness there, and nothing more.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="stanza">
                <l>Deep into that darkness peering, long I stood there wondering, fearing,</l>
                <l>Doubting, dreaming dreams no mortal ever dared to dream before;</l>
                <l>But the silence was unbroken, and the darkness gave no token,</l>
                <l>And the only word there spoken was the whispered word, “Lenore!”</l>
                <l>This I whispered, and an echo murmured back the word, “Lenore!”</l>
                <l>Merely this, and nothing more.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="stanza">
                <l>Back into the chamber turning, all my soul within me burning,</l>
                <pb n="2"/>
                <l>Soon I heard again a tapping somewhat louder than before.</l>
                <l>“Surely,” said I, “surely that is something at my window lattice;</l>
                <l>Let me see, then, what thereat is, and this mystery explore—</l>
                <l>Let my heart be still a moment and this mystery explore;—</l>
                <l>'Tis the wind and nothing more!”</l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="stanza">
                <l>Open here I flung the shutter, when, with many a flirt and flutter,</l>
                <l>In there stepped a stately raven of the saintly days of yore;</l>
                <l>Not the least obeisance made he; not an instant stopped or stayed he;</l>
                <l>But, with mien of lord or lady, perched above my chamber door—</l>
                <l>Perched upon a bust of Pallas just above my chamber door—</l>
                <l>Perched, and sat, and nothing more.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="stanza">
                <l>Then this ebony bird beguiling my sad fancy into smiling,</l>
                <l>By the grave and stern decorum of the countenance it wore,</l>
                <l>“Though thy crest be shorn and shaven, thou,” I said, “art sure no craven,</l>
                <l>Ghastly grim and ancient raven wandering from the Nightly shore—</l>
                <l>Tell me what thy lordly name is on the Night's Plutonian shore!”</l>
                <l>Quoth the raven, “Nevermore.”</l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="stanza">
                <l>Much I marvelled this ungainly fowl to hear discourse so plainly,</l>
                <l>Though its answer little meaning—little relevancy bore;</l>
                <l>For we cannot help agreeing that no living human being</l>
                <l>Ever yet was blessed with seeing bird above his chamber door—</l>
                <l>Bird or beast upon the sculptured bust above his chamber door,</l>
                <l>With such name as “Nevermore.”</l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="stanza">
                <l>But the raven, sitting lonely on the placid bust, spoke only</l>
                <l>That one word, as if his soul in that one word he did outpour.</l>
                <l>Nothing farther then he uttered—not a feather then he fluttered—</l>
                <l>Till I scarcely more than muttered “Other friends have flown before—</l>
                <l>On the morrow he will leave me, as my hopes have flown before.”</l>
                <l>Then the bird said “Nevermore.”</l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="stanza">
                <l>Startled at the stillness broken by reply so aptly spoken,</l>
                <l>“Doubtless,” said I, “what it utters is its only stock and store</l>
                <l>Caught from some unhappy master whom unmerciful Disaster</l>
                <l>Followed fast and followed faster till his songs one burden bore—</l>
                <pb n="3"/>
                <l>Till the dirges of his Hope that melancholy burden bore</l>
                <l>Of 'Never—nevermore,'"</l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="stanza">
                <l>This I sat engaged in guessing, but no syllable expressing</l>
                <l>To the fowl whose fiery eyes now burned into my bosom's core;</l>
                <l>This and more I sat divining, with my head at ease reclining</l>
                <l>On the cushion's velvet lining that the lamplight gloated o'er,</l>
                <l>But whose velvet violet lining with the lamplight gloating o'er,</l>
                <l>She shall press, ah, nevermore!</l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="stanza">
                <l>Then, methought, the air grew denser, perfumed from an unseen censer</l>
                <l>Swung by angels whose faint foot-falls tinkled on the tufted floor.</l>
                <l>“Wretch,” I cried, “thy God hath lent thee—by these angels he hath sent thee</l>
                <l>Respite—respite and nepenthe from thy memories of Lenore!</l>
                <l>Quaff, oh quaff this kind nepenthe and forget this lost Lenore!”</l>
                <l>Quoth the raven, “Nevermore.”</l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="stanza">
                <l>“Prophet!” said I, “thing of evil!—prophet still, if bird or devil!—</l>
                <l>Whether Tempter sent, or whether tempest tossed thee here ashore,</l>
                <l>Desolate yet all undaunted, on this desert land enchanted—</l>
                <l>On this home by Horror haunted—tell me truly, I implore—</l>
                <l>Is there—is there balm in Gilead?—tell me—tell me, I implore!”</l>
                <l>Quoth the raven, “Nevermore.” </l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="stanza">
                <l>“Be that word our sign of parting, bird or fiend!” I shrieked, upstarting—</l>
                <l>“Get thee back into the tempest and the Night's Plutonian shore!</l>
                <l>Leave no black plume as a token of that lie thy soul hath spoken!</l>
                <l>Leave my loneliness unbroken!—quit the bust above my door!</l>
                <l>Take thy beak from out my heart, and take thy form from off my door!”</l>
                <l>Quoth the raven, “Nevermore.”</l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="stanza">
                <l>And the raven, never flitting, still is sitting, still is sitting</l>
                <l>On the pallid bust of Pallas just above my chamber door;</l>
                <l>And his eyes have all the seeming of a demon's that is dreaming,</l>
                <l>And the lamp-light o'er him streaming throws his shadow on the floor;</l>
                <l>And my soul from out that shadow that lies floating on the floor</l>
                <l>Shall be lifted—nevermore!</l>
            </lg>
        </div>
        <pb n="4"/>
        <div type="story">
            <head>THE ANGEL OF THE ODD.</head>
            <head>AN EXTRAVAGANZA</head>

            <p> It was a chilly November afternoon. I had just consummated an unusually hearty
                dinner, of which the dyspeptic truffe formed not the least important item, and was
                sitting alone in the dining-room, with my feet upon the fender, and at my elbow a
                small table which I had rolled up to the fire, and upon which were some apologies
                for dessert, with some miscellaneous bottles of wine, spirit, and liqueur. In the
                morning I had been reading Glover's Leonidas, Wilkies Epigoniad, Lamartine's
                Pilgrimage, Barlow's Columbiad, Tuckermann's Sicily, and Griswold's Curiosities; I
                am willing to confess, therefore, that I now felt a little stupid. I made effort to
                arouse myself by aid of frequent Lafitte2, and, all failing, I betook myself to a
                stray newspaper in despair. Having carefully perused the column of "houses to let,"
                and the column of "dogs lost," and then the two columns of "wives and apprentices
                runaway," I attacked with great resolution the editorial matter, and, reading it
                from beginning to end without understanding a syllable, conceived the possibility of
                its being Chinese, and so re-read it from the end to the beginning, but with no more
                satisfactory result. I was about throwing away, in disgust, 
                
                        “This folio of four pages, happy work, 
                        Which not even poets criticise,” 
                
                when I felt my attention somewhat aroused by the paragraph which follows: 
                "The avenues to death are numerous and strange. A London paper mentions 
                the decease of a person from a singular cause. He was playing at 'puff the dart,' 
                which is played with a long needle inserted in some worsted, and blown at a target 
                through a tin tube. He placed the needle at the wrong end of the tube, and drawing 
                his breath strongly to puff the dart forward with force, drew the needle into his 
                throat. It entered the lungs, and in a few days killed him."</p>
            
           <p>Upon seeing this I fell into a great rage, without exactly knowing why. "This thing,"
                I exclaimed, "is a contemptible falsehood-a poor hoax-the lees of the invention of
                some pitiable penny-a-liner-of some wretched concoctor of accidents in Cocaigne.
                These fellows, knowing the extravagant gullibility of the age, set their wits to
                work in the imagination of improbable possibilities-of odd accidents, as they term
                them; but to a reflecting intellect (like mine," I added, in parenthesis, putting my
                forefinger unconsciously to the side of my nose), "to a contemplative understanding
                such as I myself possess, it seems evident at 
                <pb n="5"/> 
                once that the marvelous increase of late in these 'odd accidents' is by far the 
                oddest accident of all. For my own part, I intend to believe nothing henceforward 
                that has anything of the 'singular' about it.</p>
            
            <p>"Mein Gott, den, vat a vool you bees for dat!"3 replied one of the most remarkable
                voices I ever heard. At first I took it for a rumbling in my ears-such as man
                sometimes experiences when getting very drunk-but, upon second thought, I considered
                the sound as more nearly resembling that which proceeds from an empty barrel beaten
                with a big stick; and, in fact, this I should have concluded it to be, but for the
                articulation of the syllables and words. I am by no means naturally nervous, and the
                very few glasses of Lafitte which I had sipped served to embolden me a little, so
                that I felt nothing of trepidation, but merely uplifted my eyes with a leisurely
                movement, and looked carefully around the room for the intruder. I could not,
                however, perceive any one at all.</p>
            
            <p>"Humph!" resumed the voice, as I continued my survey, "you mus pe so dronk as de
                pig, den, for not zee me as I zit here at your zide."</p>
            
            <p>Hereupon I bethought me of looking immediately before my nose, and there, sure
                enough, confronting me at the table sat a personage nondescript, although not
                altogether indescribable. His body was a wine-pipe, or a rum-puncheon, or something
                of that character, and had a truly Falstaffian air. In its nether extremity were
                inserted two kegs, which seemed to answer all the purposes of legs. For arms there
                dangled from the upper portion of the carcass two tolerably long bottles, with the
                necks outward for hands. All the head that I saw the monster possessed of was one of
                those Hessian canteens which resemble a large snuff-box with a hole in the middle of
                the lid. This canteen (with a funnel on its top, like a cavalier cap slouched over
                the eyes) was set on edge upon the puncheon, with the hole toward myself; and
                through this hole, which seemed puckered up like the mouth of a very precise old
                maid, the creature was emitting certain rumbling and grumbling noises which he
                evidently intended for intelligible talk.</p>
            <p>"I zay," said he, "you mos pe dronk as de pig, vor zit dare and not zee me zit ere;
                and I zay, doo, you most pe pigger vool as de goose, vor to dispelief vat iz print
                in de print. 'Tiz de troof-dat it iz-eberry vord ob it." "Who are you, pray?" said
                I, with much dignity, although somewhat puzzled; "how did you get here? and what is
                it you are talking about?"</p>
            
            <p>"Az vor ow I com'd ere," replied the figure, "dat iz none of your pizzness; and as
                vor vat I be talking apout, I be talk apout vot I tink proper; and as vor who I be,
                vy dat is de very ting I com'd here for to let you zee for yourzelf."</p>
            
            <pb n="6"/>
            
            <p>"You are a drunken vagabond," said I, "and I shall ring the bell and order my footman
                to kick you into the street."</p>
            
            <p>"He! he! he!" said the fellow, "hu! hu! hu! dat you can't do."</p>
            
            <p>"Can't do!" said I, "what do you mean?-can't do what?"</p>
            
            <p>"Ring de pell," he replied, attempting a grin with his little villainous mouth.</p>
            
            <p>Upon this I made an effort to get up, in order to put my threat into execution; but
                the ruffian just reached across the table very deliberately, and hitting me a tap on
                the forehead with the neck of one of the long bottles, knocked me back into the
                arm-chair from which I had half arisen. I was utterly astounded; and, for a moment,
                was quite at a loss what to do. In the meantime, he continued his talk.</p>
            
            <p>"You zee," said he, "it iz te bess vor zit still; and now you shall know who I pe.
                Look at me! zee! I am te ANGEL OV TE ODD!"</p>
            
            <p>"And odd enough, too," I ventured to reply; "but I was always under the impression
                that an angel had wings."</p>
            
            <p>"Te wing!" he cried, highly incensed, "vat I pe do mit te wing? Mein Gott! do you
                take me vor a shicken?"</p>
            
            <p>"No-oh, no!" I replied, much alarmed, "you are no chicken-certainly not."</p>
            
            <p>"Well, den, zit still and pehabe yourself, or I'll rap you again mid me vist. It iz
                te shicken ab te wing, und te owl ab te wing, und te imp ab te wing, und te
                headteuffel ab te wing. Te angel ab NOT te wing, and I am te ANGEL OV TE ODD."</p>
            
            <p>"And your business with me at present is-is-"</p>
            
            <p>"My pizzness!" ejaculated the thing, "vy vot a low bred puppy you mos pe vor to ask a
                gentleman und an angel apout his pizzness!"</p>
            
            <p>This language was rather more than I could bear, even from an angel; so, plucking up
                courage, I seized a salt-cellar which lay within reach, and hurled it at the head of
                the intruder. Either he dodged, however, or my aim was inaccurate; for all I
                accomplished was the demolition of the crystal which protected the dial of the clock
                upon the mantelpiece. As for the Angel, he evinced his sense of my assault by giving
                me two or three hard consecutive raps upon the forehead as before. These reduced me
                at once to submission, and I am almost ashamed to confess that, either through pain
                or vexation, there came a few tears into my eyes.</p>
            
            <p>"Mein Gott!" said the Angel of the Odd, apparently much softened at my distress;
                "mein Gott, te man is eder ferry dronck or ferry sorry. You mos not trink it so
                strong-you mos put de water in te wine. Here, trink dis, like a goot veller, und
                don't gry now-don't!"</p>
            
            <gap reason="abridgement"/>

        </div>
        <pb n="7"/>
        <div type="drama">
            <head>SCENES FROM “POLITIAN;”<lb/> 
                AN UNPUBLISHED DRAMA.</head>

            <div type="scene" n="1">
                <head>I.</head>
                <stage>ROME.—A Hall in a Palace. Alessandra and Castiglione.</stage>

                <sp>
                    <speaker>Alessandra.</speaker>
                    <l>Thou art sad, Castiglione.</l>
                </sp>

                <sp>
                    <speaker>Castiglione.</speaker>
                    <l>Sad!—not I. </l>
                    <l>Oh, I'm the happiest, happiest man in Rome! </l>
                    <l>A few days more, thou knowest, my Alessandra, </l>
                    <l>Will make thee mine. Oh, I am very happy!</l>
                </sp>

                <sp>
                    <speaker>Aless.</speaker>
                    <l>Methinks thou hast a singular way of showing</l>
                    <l>Thy happiness!—what ails thee, cousin of mine? </l>
                    <l>Why didst thou sigh so deeply?</l>
                </sp>
                <sp>
                    <speaker>Cas.</speaker>
                    <l>Did I sigh? </l>
                    <l>I was not conscious of it. It is a fashion, </l>
                    <l>A silly—a most silly fashion I have </l>
                    <l>When I am very happy. Did I sigh?</l>
                    <stage>(sighing.)</stage>
                </sp>

                <pb n="8"/>

                <sp>
                    <speaker>Aless.</speaker>
                    <l>Thou didst. Thou art not well. Thou hast indulged </l>
                    <l>Too much of late, and I am vexed to see it. </l>
                    <l>Late hours and wine, Castiglione,—these </l>
                    <l>Will ruin thee! thou art already altered— </l>
                    <l>Thy looks are haggard—nothing so wears away </l>
                    <l>The constitution as late hours and wine.</l>
                </sp>

                <sp>
                    <speaker>Cas.</speaker>
                    <stage>(musing.)</stage>
                    <l>Nothing, fair cousin, nothing—not even deep sorrow—</l>
                    <l>Wears it away like evil hours and wine. </l>
                    <l>I will amend.</l>
                </sp>

                <sp>
                    <speaker>Aless.</speaker>
                    <l>Do it! I would have thee drop </l>
                    <l>Thy riotous company, too—fellows low born— </l>
                    <l>Ill suit the like with old Di Broglio's heir </l>
                    <l>And Alessandra's husband.</l>
                </sp>

                <sp>
                    <speaker>Cas.</speaker>
                    <l>I will drop them.</l>
                </sp>

                <sp>
                    <speaker>Aless.</speaker>
                    <l>Thou wilt—thou must. Attend thou also more </l>
                    <l>To thy dress and equipage—they are over plain </l>
                    <l>For thy lofty rank and fashion—much depends </l>
                    <l>Upon appearances.</l>
                </sp>
                <sp>
                    <speaker>Cas.</speaker>
                    <l>I'll see to it.</l>
                </sp>

                <sp>
                    <speaker>Aless.</speaker>
                    <l>Then see to it!—pay more attention, sir, </l>
                    <l>To a becoming carriage—much thou wantest </l>
                    <l>In dignity.</l>
                </sp>

                <pb n="9"/>

                <sp>
                    <speaker>Cas.</speaker>
                    <l>Much, much, oh much I want </l>
                    <l>In proper dignity.</l>
                </sp>

                <sp>
                    <speaker>Aless.</speaker>
                    <stage>(haughtily.)</stage>
                    <l>Thou mockest me, sir!</l>
                </sp>

                <sp>
                    <speaker>Cas.</speaker>
                    <stage>(abstractedly.)</stage>
                    <l>Sweet, gentle Lalage!</l>
                </sp>

                <sp>
                    <speaker>Aless.</speaker>
                    <l>Heard I aright? </l>
                    <l>I speak to him—he speaks of Lalage! </l>
                    <l>Sir Count! <stage>(places her hand on his shoulder)</stage></l>
                    <l>What art thou dreaming? he's not well! </l>
                    <l>What ails thee, sir?</l>
                </sp>

                <sp>
                    <speaker>Cas.</speaker>
                    <stage>(starting.)</stage>
                    <l>Cousin! fair cousin!—madam! </l>
                    <l>I crave thy pardon—indeed I am not well— </l>
                    <l>Your hand from off my shoulder, if you please. </l>
                    <l>This air is most oppressive!—Madam—the Duke!</l>
                </sp>

                <stage>Enter Di Broglio.</stage>

                <sp>
                    <speaker>Di Broglio.</speaker>
                    <l>My son, I've news for thee!—hey?—what's the matter?</l>
                    <stage>(observing Alessandra.)</stage>
                    <l>I' the pouts? Kiss her, Castiglione! kiss her, </l>
                    <l>You dog! and make it up, I say, this minute!</l>
                    <l>I've news for you both. Politian is expected </l>
                    <l>Hourly in Rome—Politian, Earl of Leicester! </l>
                    <l>We'll have him at the wedding. 'Tis his first visit </l>
                    <l>To the imperial city.</l>
                </sp>

            </div>
        </div>
    </body>
    <pb n="10"/>
    <back>
        <div type="notes">
            <head>NOTES.</head>
            <p>
            1"Lenore" is also the title character of another Poe poem published in 1843, two years before "The Raven".
            2Château Lafite, one of the world's most sought-after red wines, is mentioned in several Poe short stories.
            3Poe apparently invented the strange dialect spoken by the angel in the story.
            </p> 
        </div>
    </back>
</text>
