<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Title</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Information about the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         
         <!-- Parker journal -->
         <p>The only other date I find in connection with Parker occurs in Hamersly's Register of the U.S. Navy, (Washington, D.C., 1882,) which states that he entered the ___ Navy as Mate, 24 Feb. 1862, and was "dead". Maj. Gen. John C. Fremont, U.S.A., of the Western Department, reached his H.Q, at St. Louis on the 10 gun paddle steamer Mississippi, July 25, 1861, and with him was associated Commander, John Rodgers + R.N. Stembel, etc of the Navy. Cairo, at the mouth of the Ohio, was made secure, and U.S. Grant, B. Gen of Volunteers, was there established, Aug. 28, in command of South east Missouri. About the same time Fremont directed the construction of a number of mortar-boats or rafts, (to be moved by steamer tugs,) ? ?, and ? was commenced, as well as an ironclad gunboat, "the Essex," and Benton, the former was altered from a large ferry boat, called "the New Era", and carrying from 9 to 12 guns. the Benton had a seven gun boat, the "Submarine" Sept. 6, Capt. Andrew H. Foote arrived at St. Louis, as Flag Officer of the "Western Flotilla on the Mississippi"; ...</p>
         
         <fw type="runninghead">Brandywine" 1843 +'44</fw><!-- forme work: includes running titles, catchwords, signatures, page #s... -->
         
         <p>Wednesday December 20. 1843, at 2pm. We got underway, saluted Columbo with 21 guns, with the English Flag at the fore, + went to Sea. The next day passing Point de Galle, where boats came with articles - precious stones etc - for sale. In fact at Bombay + Ceylon our ship was daily crowded with men having "? stones" Cats Eyes - topaz - cornelians etc. for sale. Dubash is the name there for the providers of ships.</p> 
         <p>Thursday Dec. 21st, witnessed almost a total eclipse of the Sun, lasting 4 hours. At 8p.m. Christmas day we crossed the Equator now the 3rd time We have lost a few men from dysentery. January 1, 1844 - The Commodore gave a dinner to the officers + two of his large hogs to the crew He brought our several from home for the purpose of giving them to the crew on holidays. The American Brig Antelope, from Bombay for China, with the Parsian Embassy on board, passed us at Sea. January 18th. We passed Sandalwood Island. + say a number of most perfect water sports. On 19th. we made the Island of Java to the N? + E? of us; also saw the Volcanoes on the Id of Flores? distant 100 or so? miles. The night of January 20th. passed thru the Ombay? passage, between Timor + Ombay Islands. In the Banda Sea had light rain + adverse current + had time to get round Boars? Island. February 2d 1844, crossed the Equator for the 4th time, + entered the North Pacific Ocean. During the past month we cought 10,000 falls. of rain water. Sunday Feb. 11th. passed the Pilew Islands + on 19th passed byt the Richmond Rocks + Bashee? group, into the China Sea.</p>
         
         
         <!-- Printing from the Other Europe bibliography -->
         
         <!-- Title page -->
         <p>HEVELIUS, Johannes. Selenographia, sive, Lunae descriptio; atque accurata, tam macularum ejus, quam mottum diversorum, aliarumque omnium vicissitudinum, phasiumque, telescopii ope deprehensarum, delineatio : in quâsimul caeterorum omnium planetarum nativa facies, variaeque observationes ... sub aspectum ponuntur ... : Addita est, lentes expoliendi nova ratio.... Gdansk, Hünefeldianis, 1647</p>
         
         <p>2°, [593] p., 95 leaves of plates, with 3 double-page plates, 19 leaves printed on both sides. Extra engraved title inserted after half-title. Bound in old vellum, handwritten title on spine. Bookplates of Ferdinand Faber and Samuel Verplanck Hoffman.</p>
         
         <p>The first detailed lunar atlas, depicting more than 200 lunar formations. With the invention of the telescope in the early 17th century, astronomers could map the planets and constellations just as cartographers were mapping the geography of the earth. As the closest object to the earth, the moon quickly became a favorite object of study for many astronomers. One of the greatest of these astronomers was Jan Hevelius (1611-1687), born in Gdansk. In Selenographia, Hevelius created an authoritative atlas and study of the moon derived from his own observations. Hevelius had one of the most well-equipped observatories in Europe, covering the rooftops of several buildings, complete with a revolving observation hut, telescopes and astronomical instruments which he made himself, and even a printing press to produce his copperplate engravings. The majority of plates were engraved by Hevelius in his observatory where he could produce the most detailed and accurate illustrations. The volume contains 133 engraved plates depicting the moon and its phases, as well as illustrations of the instruments he created. This is perhaps Hevelius’ greatest work.</p>
         
         <p>References: NUC pre-1956, 244:266; BM, 103:256; Sotheran, Bibl. chem.-math., 1913</p>
         
      </body>
      <back>
         
         <!-- Notes -->
         <div type="notes">
            
         </div>
         
         <div type="editorial">
            
            <!-- Personography -->   
            <listPerson>
               <person xml:id="">
                  <persName></persName>
                  <birth when=""></birth>
                  <death when=""></death>
               </person>
            </listPerson>
            
               <!-- Bibliography -->
               <listBibl>
                  
               </listBibl>
               
               <!-- Placeography -->
               <listPlace>
                  <place type="" xml:id="">
                     <placeName></placeName>
                     <location>
                        <geo><!-- coordinates --></geo>
                     </location>
                  </place>
               </listPlace>
               
               <!-- Shipography -->
               <list type="ships">
                  <item xml:id="">
                     <name ref=""></name>
                     <desc></desc>
                  </item>
               </list>
               
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
